Administering
the Code
Part 2 of the Code includes procedures designed to provide an effective and efficient 
complaint-handling process, at national and MedTech Europe level, to ensure compliance 
with the Code. MedTech EuropeÆs dispute handling system is based on the principle that 
disputes are generally national in nature and are therefore best resolved at national level. 
For complaints between Member Companies, mediation should be considered seriously 
before further pursuit of the matter via any formal complaint handling process, either at 
national or MedTech Europe level.
The principles outlined in Part 2: Complaint handling and dispute resolution also aim at 
supporting Member Associations when setting up or amending their national 
dispute-resolution mechanisms. They are based on principles of proportionality, speed, due 
process, fairness and transparency and have been established under the guidance of the 
MedTech Europe Compliance Panel, acting independently of MedTech Europe.  
The Code shall be reviewed when required and at a minimum every five (5) years, in 
accordance with the governance rules of MedTech Europe.


--- PAGE 10 ---
MEDTECH EUROPE û CODE OF ETHICAL BUSINESS PRACTICE
QUESTIONS AND ANSWERS
10
ADMINISTERING THE CODE
1. The Conference Vetting System
The Conference Vetting System is an independently-managed system which reviews the 
compliance of Third Party Organised Educational Events with the Code.
Conference Vetting System (see the Glossary) has been established as the online, binding 
and centralised decision-making process to help Member Companies review the compliance 
of relevant Third Party Organised Educational Events with the Code.  It is managed 
independently of the MedTech Europe Secretariat and Members and is under the supervision 
of the MedTech Europe Compliance Panel.
The Conference Vetting System approval is required for Members to support Third Party 
Organised Educational Events which fall within its scope, as provided in Annex I.
Where there is a Conference Vetting System decision in relation to a specific Third Party 
Organised Educational Event, this decision is binding upon all Member Companies.
2. MedTech Europe Code Committee
The MedTech Europe Code Committee shall assist Member Associations and Member 
Companies to comply with their obligations under the Code, including the dispute resolution 
principles set out in Part 2 of the Code.
As a key part of its role, the MedTech Europe Code Committee shall promote the Code, 
monitor the adoption of compliant national codes, including preparation of updates to the 
MedTech Europe Board and assist Member Companies and Member Associations to share 
best practice and harmonised interpretation of the Code and its dispute resolution principles.
The MedTech Europe Code Committee will be composed of:
ò	 at least one (1) but up to three (3) representatives of the MedTech Europe Legal Affairs 
Committee, elected in accordance with its own procedures, with a preference for the 
members of the MedTech Europe Legal Affairs CommitteeÆs Steering Committee
ò	 nine (9) representatives of the MedTech Europe Ethics & Compliance Committee, elected 
in accordance with its own procedures
ò	 the Chair of the MedTech Europe Ethics & Compliance Committee
ò	 at least one (1) but up to three (3) representatives from Member Associations, elected in 
accordance with its own procedures
ò	 In addition, the Code Committee may co-opt up to four (4) other members from the 


--- PAGE 11 ---
MEDTECH EUROPE û CODE OF ETHICAL BUSINESS PRACTICE
QUESTIONS AND ANSWERS
11
ADMINISTERING THE CODE
MedTech Europe Legal Affairs Committee and the MedTech Europe Ethics & Compliance 
Committee, where the Code Committee is satisfied that the concerned members 
will positively enhance the representativeness, operation and objectives of the Code 
Committee.
ò	 Only one representative from a Member may be a member of the Code Committee at any 
given time
ò	 The MedTech Europe Compliance Panel and the Conference Vetting System officers shall 
automatically be non-voting members of the Code Committee
ò	 The Code Committee may invite external lawyers as standing non-voting members, as 
needed.
The Code Committee will elect its Chair from among the members of the group for renewable 
periods of two years, or until the Chair ceases to be a member of the Code Committee. The 
Chairs of other MedTech Europe committees are not eligible to be at the same time Chair of 
the Code Committee. 
3. MedTech Europe Compliance Panel
1. Tasks
The MedTech Europe Compliance Panel shall have the following tasks:
ò	 Supervise the MedTech Europe Conference Vetting System.
ò	 Review consistency with the Code of interpretations of national panels of nationally 
applicable codes of conduct, upon request of the MedTech Europe Code Committee;
ò	 Provide guidance to Member Associations on the dispute resolution principles set out in 
Part 2 of the Code;
ò	 Interact, upon request of the Secretariat, with relevant MedTech Europe groups to further 
develop the Code and guidance documents;
The MedTech Europe Board may allocate additional tasks to the MedTech Europe Compliance 
Panel as deemed appropriate. 
As an independent body, the MedTech Europe Compliance Panel shall be entitled to report to 
the MedTech Europe Code Committee any concerns that it might encounter in the exercise 
of its functions.
2. Composition


--- PAGE 12 ---
MEDTECH EUROPE û CODE OF ETHICAL BUSINESS PRACTICE
QUESTIONS AND ANSWERS
12
ADMINISTERING THE CODE
The MedTech Europe Compliance Panel will be composed of at least three individuals. 
These shall include not only persons having industry experience but also for obvious reasons 
of  independence, transparency and expertise, persons whose knowledge will contribute to 
the proper functioning of the MedTech Europe Compliance Panel, such as other relevant 
stakeholders and whose position may not raise potential conflicts of interest, in particular as 
regards complaint handling processes. 
The chair of the MedTech Europe Compliance Panel must have a legal background. Neither 
the chair nor any member of the Compliance Panel can be employed by, or be contracted as 
a consultant for, a Member Company or an entity affiliated to a Member Company or by a 
Member Association or a company member of such Member Association. For avoidance of 
doubt, holding a position on the Board of Directors of a Member Association without any 
consulting or employment relationship with a Member Company shall not be considered a 
consultant or employee relationship with the concerned Member. 
If for any reason a potential conflict of interest of a member of the MedTech Europe 
Compliance Panel occurs, then the concerned member shall refrain from participating in the 
specific complaint handling and decision process. 
The term of office of the MedTech Europe Compliance Panel members will be three years, 
renewable twice. The chair shall appoint two other individuals for the MedTech Europe 
Compliance Panel, after consultation with and consent of the MedTech Europe Code 
Committee and the MedTech Europe Secretariat. The term of office of the two other MedTech 
Europe Compliance Panel members will also be three years and may be renewed twice by the 
chair, after consultation with and consent of the MedTech Europe Code Committee and the 
MedTech Europe Secretariat. 
Notwithstanding the foregoing, the MedTech Europe Board may decide on different terms 
of office in order to ensure a staggered rotation of the three MedTech Europe Compliance 
Panel members, provided, however, that the MedTech Europe Compliance Panel member 
has given his/her consent.  
3. MedTech Europe Compliance Panel Internal Procedural Rules
The MedTech Europe Compliance Panel may develop, after consultation with and consent 
of the MedTech Europe Code Committee, Internal Procedural Rules to hear and decide on 
disputes or questions of interpretation. These Internal Procedural Rules shall be based on the 
principles of Part 2 of the Code.
4. Interpreting the Code


--- PAGE 13 ---
MEDTECH EUROPE û CODE OF ETHICAL BUSINESS PRACTICE
QUESTIONS AND ANSWERS
13
ADMINISTERING THE CODE
The use of capital letters indicates that a word or expression is a defined term, the meaning 
of which is set out in the Glossary.
Any phrase introduced by the terms: including, include, in particular, or any similar 
expression shall be interpreted as illustrative and shall not limit the sense of the words 
preceding those terms.
Promoting an Ethical Industry


--- PAGE 14 ---
MEDTECH EUROPE û CODE OF ETHICAL BUSINESS PRACTICE
QUESTIONS AND ANSWERS
14
ADMINISTERING THE CODE
